Register of the Heinrich Himmler papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Heinrich Himmler papers
1914-1945
XX060
Hoover Institution Archives
15 manuscript boxes, 5 microfilm reels, 2 photo albums, 6 diaries, 27 sound tape reels (8.1 linear feet)
Diaries (1914-1924); photographs; photocopies and microfilm of correspondence, reports, and memoranda from the office files of the personal staff of Heinrich Himmler (1942-1944); and recordings of speeches by Himmler (1940-1944) relating to national socialism in Germany, and activities of the German police and Schutzstaffel during World War II. In part, photocopy and microfilm. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Himmler, Heinrich, 1900-1945.
Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei. Reichsführer-SS. Persönlicher Stab. Schriftgutverwaltung.
Access
Collection is open for research. The two photo albums are closed, but digital use copies of them are available in the reading room and online at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in the German Bundesarchiv.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
Reichsführer SS und Chef der deutschen Polizei, 1934-1945.
Scope and Content
The Heinrich Himmler papers are largely comprised of a set of photostat documents of the Persönlicher Stab der Reichsführer-SS. The originals of these papers were located in a salt mine in the Salzburg region and seized in 1945 by American forces. In 1946 they were filmed at the Berlin Document Center. These office files include internal office memoranda, correspondence, case files, reports, telegrams, cables, copies of periodicals, remarks, statements, decrees, clippings, drawings, and press releases relating to a variety of topics. The collection also includes speeches and writings, correspondence, diaries, photo albums, and sound recordings.
Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei. Schutzstaffel.; National socialism.; Police--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; Statesmen--Germany.; Audiotapes.
- Persönlicher Stab der Reichsführer-SS Office Files, 1936-1945
  - Office of Military Government for Germany (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Order forms for microfilming and photostatting.
  - File 51. Internal office records of the Personal Staff of the Reichsführer of the SS, 1936-1944
    Contains miscellaneous personnel and non-personnel case files.
    - Cases #1-7 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Case #8 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      Case file on W. G. L. Yeats
    - Cases #10-21 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Case #22 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Cases #23-25 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - File 52. Internal office records of the Personal Staff of the Reichsführer of the SS, 1938-1944
    - Cases #1-6 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Cases #7-12 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Cases #13-25 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      Files #24-25 relate to the status of Vichy Ambassador Scapini and Vidkun Quisling's visit to Berlin.
  - File 53. SS-Gruppenführer Dr. Gustav Adolf Scheel, Gauleiter and Reich Governor of Salzburg, 1941 October - 1943 June (Box-folder 1: 10)
    Includes medical examination.
  - File 65. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - File 66. Correspondence between Reichsführer-SS Himmler and SS-Obergruppenführer Hauser, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - File 67. The Grundstückgesellschaft of the Haupttreuhandlungsstelle Ost and its director Friedrich Stein, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - File 68. SS-General Erwin Rösner, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    Includes letters between Reichsführer-SS Himmler and Rösner.
  - File 69. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - File 70. Security Police Chief Reinhard Heydrich, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 2: 5-8)
    Includes materials relating to his death, funeral, and the Heydrich family. Also includes correspondence between Lina Heydrich and Reichsführer-SS Himmler.
  - File 251. The Ethnic German Office (Volksdeutsche Mittelstelle) under SS-Obergruppenführer Werner Lorenz and resettlement camps (Umsiedlerlagern), 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - File 252. Partisan activities in German occupied countries, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - File 253. Transfer of a few Ordnungspolizei and Sicherheitspolizei to the SS, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - File 254. Replacement and conscription of physicians in the Waffen-SS, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - File 255. The SS-School Haus Wewelsburg, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - File 256. Deployment of a flotilla to the Ijsselmeer for defensive purposes, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - File 257. The Office of Environmental Planning (Reischsstelle Raumordnung), 1936-1944 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - File 258. Jacques le Conte and the Villmorin Company, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - File 259. Miscellaneous internal office memoranda, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - File 260. Deployment of the Germanische SS-Division, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - File 261. The Germanic Regional Headquarters (Germanische Leitstelle), 1941-1944 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    Includes correspondence between Martin Borman and Reichsführer Himmler.
  - File 262. Search for natural resources in occupied Ukraine, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - File 263. The Ukraine SS-Schützen-Division Galizien Nr. 1, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - File 264. Governor Renteln of Lithuania and the formation of the Lithuanian volunteer units, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - File 265. The upbringing of orphaned SS-children, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - File 266. Resettlement of evacuated Germans in Zamość district, Poland, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
  - File 268. The military and political situation in the Allied armies, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - File 269. Memorandum by Reichsführer-SS Himmler addressing the morale of the SS men, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - File 270. SS-translators, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - File 271. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - File 272. Employment of White Russian émigrés in the German police service in Serbia, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - File 273. Indexes to maps on important geological deposits in European Russia (Wehrgeologische Karten des Europäischen Russland), 1943 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - File 274-276. Recruitment of German volunteers in Hungary, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 11-13)
  - File 277. The Katyn Massacre, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - File 278. Recruitment of SA men, foreign workers and citizens of occupied countries for the Waffen-SS, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - File 279. Sabotage and occupation of St. Mihiel and Avignon, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - File 280. Miscellaneous internal office memoranda, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    Includes correspondence to and from Martin Borman and a memorandum relating to the Ostarbeiter.
  - File 281. The Croatian SS-Division, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 5: 5-7)
  - File 282. The Army's medical service, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - File 283
    - File A. Correspondence relating to Bishop Joachim Hossenfelder's memorandum to Goebbels and Himmler concerning the "reform of Christianity,", 1943 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - File B. Medical affairs in the SS, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - File 284. German minorities in Denmark, Norway, Belgium and the Netherlands, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    Includes correspondence to and from Reichskommissar Seyss-Inquart.
  - File 285. Report relating to the periodical De Vlag, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Includes copy of De Vlag.
  - File 286. Copies of photographs and internal office memoranda relating to the publication of Der Untermensch, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
    Includes a copy of Das 12 Uhr Blatt.
  - File 287. The Ordnungspolizei, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - File 288. Construction of the Weimar-Buchenwald rail-line, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 6: 5-6)
  - File 289. SS cooperation in the struggle against the "black market,", 1942-1943 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - File 290. "Aktion Wieland," the search for new natural resources in Galicia, Poland and the Ukraine [see also: File 360], 1943-1944 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - File 290. "Aktion Wieland,", 1942-1945 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
  - File 291. German employers' treatment of workers from occupied Eastern countries (Ostarbeiter) (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - File 292. Medical experiments (lead poisoning) on concentration camp inmates, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - File 293. The Technical High School in Lina, 1943 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - File 294. The problem of recompensing expropriated Poles in the General Government, 1942 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - File 295. Improvements in the camouflaging of military object, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - File 296. Regulations permitting SS marriages and divorces, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - File 297. Miscellaneous internal office memoranda, 1943 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - File 298. Correspondence by Albert Speer, Minister of Weapons and Munitions, to the Reichsführer for German Arms Industry, 1943 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - File 299. Military training of ethnic Germans in Scandinavia, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - File 300. Occupation of Serbia and its administration by the Germans, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - File 301. Military postal service, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - File 302. Evacuation of women and children from Berlin, 1943 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - File 303. Correspondence between the National Socialist Movement in the Netherlands (signed by Mussert) and Reichsminister Seyss-Inquart, 1943 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - File 304. Re-Germanization of the Poles (Wiedereindeutschungsfähige Polen), 1942-1943 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - File 305. Typescript miscellaneous news reports by the German media, 1943 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - File 306. The bombing and destruction of Hamburg, 1943 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - File 307. The German minority in Poland and the re-Germanization of Poles, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    Includes the pamphlet Verpolte deutsche Familiennamen.
  - File 308. War-disabled, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - File 309. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - File 310. "Planned vacations" and Himmler's action to prevent childlessness in the families of SS-personnel, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    Includes items from File 977.
  - File 311. The Flemish National Association (Flämish National-Verband), 1943-1944 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - File 312. Teacher training, 1942 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - File 313. Building materials used for insulation and thatching roofs, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - File 314. The SS-Division composed of German-Hungarians, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    Includes biographical profile of Count Johann Joseph Wenzel Anton Franz Karl Radetsky, Fieldmarshall of Austria.
  - File 315. Miscellaneous files, undated (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - File 316. Improvement in the diets of children borne by women workers from the Eastern occupied countries (Ostarbeiter), 1942-1943 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - File 317. Employment of Soviet war prisoners of German ancestry in the German war industry, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - File 318. The Lettisch SS-Division, 1943 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - File 319. Resettlement of Germans from Russia and Bessarabia, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 10: 2-4)
  - File 320. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - File 321. The Party's sphere of influence and the Germanic regional headquarters, 1943 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - File 322. List of field post addresses of the SS units, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - File 323. Miscellaneous news reports from the German Information Office; materials relating to the labor organization of youth in occupied Ukraine; and two volumes of Alfred Fielder's Werkdienst des Reichskommissars fur die Ukraine, 1943 (Box-folder 10: 8-9)
  - File 324. Nazi Party members' parliamentary seats, 1943 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - File 325. Changes in political attitudes and spirits in Lower Styria (Slovenia), 1942-1944 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    Includes material relating to partisan activities and reprisals.
  - File 326. The illegal cumulation of a "Black account" by SS-Obergruppenführer Schmauser, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - File 327. Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - File 328. The SS-Freiwilligen-Panzergrenadier-Division "Horst Wessel,", 1944 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - File 329. Security regulations for SS offices, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - File 330. The removal from important posts of SS members "with international relations,", 1943-1945 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - File 331. Underground mining of lime in Greater Strelitz, Upper Silesia, 1944 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - File 332
    - Folder 1. The SS-Tibet-Expedition, 1939 (Box-folder 11: 9)
    - Folder 2. Mining in Galicia for oil substitutes, 1944
    - Folder 3. Military obligation for those Germans from the various ethnic groups, 1944-1945
    - Folder 4. Military waiver for the farming community, 1944
    - Folder 5. The Muslim national community in Sandjak (a district of the former Turkish Empire), Serbia, 1944
    - Folder 6. Rabam-Werk Georg Bertram and Son, 1944
    - Folder 7. Courier report on SS-J.R. 4, 1942
    - Folder 8. SS men killed in action, 1936-1938
    - Folder 10. Disposal of loot from exterminated Jews ("Sonderaktion Reinhard"), 1943-1945 (Box-folder 11: 10)
    - Folder 11. Himmler's speech given at the Convention of City Mayors in Posen, 1944 February 13
    - Folder 12. Cancellation of Reich inspection in Denmark, Slovakia and Romania, 1944
    - Folder 13. Dr. Clauberg's proposal to start experiments concerning the sterilization of women and a demand for concentration camp inmates for these experiments, 1941
    - Folder 14. Waffen-SS building contractors in Lublin, Poland, 1942 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Folder 15. Miscellaneous, 1944
    - Folder 16. Defense against increasing agent activities inside the Reich, 1944
    - Folder 17. Building of a bunker at Gmund on the Tegernsee, 1944
    - Folder 18. Miscellaneous, 1944
    - Folder 19. Miscellaneous, 1944
    - Folder 20. Sail plane Horten II, 1944
    - Folder 21. Suvorov Schools, 1944
    - Folder 22. Draft of martial law ("Sicherungsstandrecht") decree, 1944 July 20
    - Folder 23. Miscellaneous, 1944
    - Folder 25. Himmler's order banning the use of the word "Partisan,", 1942
  - File 333. New inventions submitted to Himmler for development (in alphabetical order by name of inventor), 1942-1945 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - File 334. SS-Cossack Division, 1938-1944 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    Includes reference to Krasnov and other.
  - File 335. Adriatic affairs, 1944 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - File 336. Distribution of chocolate to the Hitler Jugend, 1945 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - File 337. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - File 339. Agriculture and the Ministry for Agriculture, 1940-1945 (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - File 340. Aid for German war prisoners in Allied countries, 1944 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    Incudes copies of photographs.
  - File 341. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - File 342
    - File A. SS organization for construction ("Baudienststellen der Waffen-SS und Polizei") which built primarily concentration camps, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - File B. Conference of Reichsleiter and Gauleiter in Posen and Hitler's headquarters, 1943 October 6-7 (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - File 343
    - File A. Liquidation of the Warsaw Ghetto, 1943 (Box-folder 12: 12)
      Includes a copy of Himmler's order for the destruction of the ghetto.
    - File B. The Warsaw Uprising, 1944 (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - File 344. Evacuation of refugees from East Prussia and Danzig, 1945 and the deterioration of morale among retreating troops, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - File 351. SS-Oberführer W. Traupel, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
  - File 352. SS-Oberführer Dr. Richard Donnevert, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - File 353. SS-Gruppenführer and Generalleutnant of the Police Dr. Max Thomas, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - File 354. Gauleiter Weinrich, 1944 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - File 355. Notation indicates file missing (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - File 356. Professor Ernst Wagemann, President of the Institute for Economic Studies, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - File 357. Reorganization of the administration of all armed forces in Germany, 1944 (Box-folder 13: 9-10)
    Includes copy of Hitler's orders of 1944 July 20 and August 2.
  - File 358. Johann (Hans) Loritz, Commander of Dachau and Sachsenhausen concentration camps, 1937-1945 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - File 359. Copy of "Der rechte Mann an dem richtigen Platz! Menschenführung nach nationalsozialistischen Grundsätzen,", 1940 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - File 360. Paul Ortel of "Aktion Wieland" [see also: File 290], 1944-1945 (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - File 361. SS-Unterstrumführer Friedrich Schmidt, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - File 362. The Romanian "Iron Guard" - refugees in Germany, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    Includes reference to Romanian Foreign Minister Prince Sturdza.
  - File 365. The internal organization of the SS, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - File 370. General "Bor" Komarowski in Prisoner of War Camp Oflag IVC - Colditz, Germany, 1945 (Box-folder 14: 7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1939-1940
  - Notes, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - "Gemeindepolizei," typescript, 1939 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - "Kreisleitertagung," typescript, 1940 November 28 (Box-folder 14: 10)
- Clippings, 1937 (Box-folder 14: 11)
- Correspondence, 1917-1923
  - 1917 January - 1920 December (Box-folder 14: 12)
  - 1921 February - 1923 September (Box-folder 15: 1)
- Diaries, 1919 September 4 - 1920 February 2 (Box-folder 15: 2)
  Access
  May not be quoted.
  Typed transcript
- Photographs, 1929-1934 (Reading room workstation)
  Original photo albums closed; digital use copies available.
  Two photograph albums containing 237 prints depicting the career of Heinrich Himmler as Reichsführer SS und Chef der deutschen Polizei.
  - Album (A), 1929-1934
    Contains photographs of Himmler, including both portraits and outings with troops. Includes one photograph of Adolf Hitler.
  - Album (B), circa 1934
- Microfilm Reels, 1914-1945 (Microfilm cabinet)
  Microfilm copies of select Persönlicher Stab der Reichsführer-SS office files and diaries.
  - Files 263, 283, 286, 292, 332, 334, 342, 343 (Reel 1)
  - File 357 (Reel 2)
  - File 353 (Reel 3)
  - Positive and negative film of Himmler's diary, 1914 September 23 - 1922 July 6; 1924 February 11-25 (Reels 4-5)
- Sound Recordings, 1940-1944; 27 sound tape reels (Tape cabinet)
  - Himmler speech (fragment) to officers of a Volksgrenadier Division, 1944 July 25 - August 29; 1 sound tape reel (Reel 1)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008041
    Fragment only. May be dated 1944 August 29 only.
  - Himmler speech (fragment) to commanders of the Galician SS Volunteer Infantry Division, Neuhammer, 1944 May 16; 1 sound tape reel (Reel 2)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008042
    Incomplete, last third of speech not here. Himmler plus section by section Ukrainian translation.
  - Disjointed British and American voices, 1944 May 22; 2 sound tape reels (Reels 3-4)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008045
    Monitored broadcast, Stalag III-B. This may be a bugging of a meeting of British and American POWs in a German camp.
  - Himmler speech (fragment) to the commanders of the Ordnungspolizei and the police presidents, Posen, Hotel Ostland, 1943 December 15; 3 sound tape reels (Reels 5-7)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008046
  - Himmler speech (fragment) to the commanders of an SS Panzerkorps, Charkov, 1943 April 24; 3 sound tape reels (Reels 8-10)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008049
    See also: Reel 19
  - Himmler speech (fragment) to the commanders of the Waffen SS, Berlin, Kasino der Leibstandarte, 1940 December 18; 1 sound tape reel (Reel 11)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008050
  - Himmler speech (fragment) to the SS Führer and officials in the General Government, Krakau, 1943 November 18; 2 sound tape reels (Reels 12-13)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008052
  - Himmler speech to officers of two Volksgrenadier Divisions, Münsingen, 1944 August 27; 5 sound tape reels (Reels 14-18)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008053
  - Himmler speech (fragment) to the commanders of an SS Panzerkorps, Charkov, 1943 April 24; 1 sound tape reel (Reel 19)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008056
    See also: Reels 8-10
  - Himmler speech (incomplete) to two Volksgrenadier Divisions, Dorn, 1944 August 13; 4 sound tape reels (Reels 20-23)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008057
  - Himmler speech (fragment) or "Tag der Freiheit, Warthegau," Posen, 1943 October 24; 1 sound tape reel (Reel 24)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008058
  - Himmler speech in Posen, 1943 October 4; 3 sound tape reels (Reels 25-27)
    Use copy reference number: xx060_a_0008059